[Music]
for over a century fasting has been
espoused as a treatment of supposed
great utility in the preservation of
Health especially rejuvenating the body
but above all the mind but fast people
even just 18 hours and they get all
hungry and irritable after one or two
days positive mood goes down negative
mood goes up and by 72 hours people can
feel sad self-blaming and suffer a loss
of
libido but then something strange starts
to happen after a few days people
experience a fasting induced mood
enhancement decreased anxiety depression
fatigue and improved Vigor and that's
what studies tend to show across the
board once you get over the hump faster
frequently experience an increased level
of vigilance and mood Improvement a a
subjective feeling of well-being
sometimes even Euphoria and no wonder as
by then your endorphin levels May shoot
up nearly 50% this enhancement of mood
alertness and calm makes a certain
amount of evolutionary sense yet your
body wants you to feel crappy initially
so you continue eating day-to- day when
food is available but if you go a couple
days without food your body realizes it
can't have you moping back in the cave
you got to get motivated to get out
there and find some calories so can
fasting be used for mood disorders like
depression yeah it's great that you can
get people to feel better after a few
days of fasting but the critical
question revolves around the Persistence
of mood improvement over time once you
start eating again you don't know until
you put it to the test interestingly the
little published evidence we have comes
out of Japan and the former Soviet Union
and some of it is just ridiculous like
this study which included women with a
variety of symptoms which the
researchers blame mostly on marital
conflict oh husband not treating you
right how about a little electroshock
therapy that didn't seem to help much
though so what about Hunger therapy of
course starving those women made them
hungry but that's what Thorazine is for
if you keep injecting them with an antis
psychotic to calm them down they can
sail right through so what happened who
cares what happened what we even do with
those results right but this other study
skipped the thorine 10 days of fasting
but they also kept them in bed all day
completely isolated with no contact with
the outside world so yeah people got
better or worse it' be impossible to
tease out the effects of just the
fasting component but they did
apparently get better with efficacy
supposedly demonstrated in 31 out of 36
patients suffering from depression they
conclude that fasting therapy May
provide an alternative to the use of
anti-depressant drugs considering it a
kind of shock therapy people are so
relieved to just be eating again to get
out of solitary confinement to even just
get out of bed they report feeling
better yeah but that was at the time of
discharge how did they feel the next day
the next week the next month fasting is
by definition unsustainable so ideally
what we want to see is some kind of
longer lasting effects so what the
researchers did was follow up with a few
hundred patients not just a few months
later but a few years later of the 69
who were evidently suffering from
depression 90% reported feeling good or
excellent results at the end of The
10day Fast and remarkably years later
87% of the 62 that replied claimed that
they were still doing good now there was
no control group so we don't know if
they would have done just as well or
better without the fast and it was just
self-reports so maybe there was response
bu where you try to pleased the
researcher or maybe they were afraid
otherwise they'd get sent back to the
hole we have no idea but we do have good
evidence for the short-term mood
benefits the question is why in addition
to the endorphins when you fast the
surgeon serotonin so called Happiness
hormone there's a bump in bdnf brain
derived neurotropic Factor considered to
play a crucial role in mood disorders
and it's not just because you perk up
rodents with it humans with major
depression have lower levels circulating
in their bloodstream autopsy studies of
suicide victims show only about half the
bdnf and certain key brain regions
compared to controls suggesting may play
an important role in suicidal Behavior
you can boost BNF with anti-depressant
drugs and electroshock or with calorie
restriction a 70% boost in levels after
3 months cutting 25% of calories out of
their daily diet but is there anything
we can add to our diets to boost bdnf
levels so we can get the benefits
without the hunger we'll find out next
[Music]